<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LEAF-VRE/code_snippets/refs/heads/main/CSS/leaf.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title/>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
            <availability>
               <p>Published under unspecified terms</p>
            </availability>
            <date>2025-01-17Z</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Converted from DOCX</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      
      <xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#" xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#" xmlns:fabio="https://purl.org/spar/fabio#" xmlns:bf="http://www.openlinksw.com/schemas/bif#" xmlns:cito="https://sparontologies.github.io/cito/current/cito.html#" xmlns:org="http://www.w3.org/ns/org#"/></xenoData><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Converted from DOCX to TEI using XSLT</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <div>
               <head>Elbridge Gerry.</head>
               <p>The son of Thomas Gerry, a native of Newton, England, but emigrated to this country
                  in 1730, was born at Marblehead, Massachusetts, the 17th of July 1744. He entered
                  Harvard college before he was fourteen years of age, &amp; graduated there in
                  1762.He was at first destined to the profession of medicine, to which he was
                  strongly attached; but soon after he left college he engaged in the same business
                  his father followed &amp; at his request, that of a merchant; &amp; for some time
                  attended the routine of mercantile pur==suits in his native town. The knowlege he
                  acquired of commerce &amp; the modes of transacting that branch of business was
                  useful to him in futurelife.</p>
               <p>The strong political excitements of the times attracted hisattention from the
                  compting house, tho for the time he was successful,&amp; terminated his connection
                  with commerce, to which he had littlepartiality. In the intervals of public
                  employment he did indeedresume the avocation, but as might be expected, when not
                  steadilypursued with no great satisfaction or advantage; &amp; after a fewyears he
                  finally abandoned it for other objects more congenial tohis mind.</p>
               <p>He made his first appearance in public life as a represen==tative of his native
                  town in May 1772-a period when theroyal government &amp; people were in a high
                  state of acrimony &amp;almost open collision. The next year he was re-elected,
                  &amp; tho one ofthe youngest members, was appointed a member of the
                  standingcommittee of correspondence &amp; enquiry with the other colonies; &amp;of
                  the committee to prepare an address to the provinces. He wasdistinguished for his
                  zeal &amp; firmness in support of the rights of hiscountry. His spirit was
                  nourished by close communion with theAdamses, the Hancocks, &amp; the Warrens of
                  those days. He entered early,from principle, in opposition to British
                  encroachments, &amp; continuedone of the most uniform republicans to the end of
                  the contest. Duringthe revolution, beside his own personal exertions, which were
                  unre==mitted &amp; indefatigable, he did not hesitate, in many cases, to
                  advancehis own funds, when immediate payment was required, &amp; toincur
                  responsibities on his own credit, which the government wasthen unable to redeem,
                  &amp; which in fact, occassioned him in the endheavy pecuniary losses.</p>
               <p>In 1774, in consequence of difficulties which arose in Marblehead onaccount of the
                  small pox, he declined a re-election to the legislature.But in October he was
                  elected member of an assembly which met atSalem, &amp; adjourned to Concord, where
                  they assumed the form of a legisla==tive assembly under the name of the provincial
                  congress.</p>
               <p>In 1775 he was a member of the provincial congress of Massachusettswhich virtually
                  destroyed the royal authority in that province. He waschairman of the committee of
                  supplies to provide ammunition &amp; pro==visions, &amp; to deposit them in some
                  place of safety for future use. Thistrust he executed with great punctuality &amp;
                  unwearied industry. On the18th of April the British troops on their march to
                  Lexington, in the middleof the night, passed the house in which the committee held
                  their ses==sion. After the foremost of the troops passed, Gerry from his bed sawa
                  portion of them preparing to surround the house, he sprang fromhis bed, &amp; half
                  dressed escaped undiscovered &amp; concealed himself in acornfield, till the
                  troops entered &amp; searched the house &amp; bed chambers, andjoined the main
                  body &amp; marched off; Gerry then returned, &amp; tho his</p>
               <p>bed had been rumpled, he found his clothing &amp; watch safe.Being ardent &amp;
                  persevering in his measures to oppose the publicenemy, early in November he
                  proposed that the provincial congressshould raise a committee upon the subject of
                  fitting out armedvessels &amp; establishing a court for the trial &amp;
                  condemnation of assizes.The committee was appointed, a bill reported, &amp;
                  passed; &amp; soon after thecouncil appointed him, under the authority of that
                  Act, maritime judgefor the counties of Suffolk, Middlesex, &amp; Essex; but
                  thinking he couldbe more useful as a legislator &amp; preferring it to that of a
                  judge,he declined the appointment.</p>
               <p>On the 18th of January 1776 he was elected a delegate to the generalcongress,
                  &amp; on the 9th of February following took his seat, &amp; continuedsuch under
                  other elections till the 5th of July 1780. As a delegate he wasconstantly
                  attentive, active, industrious, exact, &amp; tenacious of public &amp;private
                  honor, &amp; rendered great service to the nation. He was a zealous&amp; able
                  advocate for the independence of this country, &amp; signed the declara==tion of
                  it. From his first entrance into congress, till the organizationof the treasury
                  board in 1780, he continued to be a member, &amp; generallychairman of the
                  committee of the treasury. In his capacity of presidingofficer of the board of the
                  treasury, he rendered himself particularlyinvidious to general Arnold, whose
                  extravagant accounts he rejectedwith a spirit which deserves admiration, as Arnold
                  was then knownonly as a gallant soldier, whose skill &amp; courage had been
                  conspicu==ously exerted for his country, &amp; the liberality with which such
                  talents &amp;activity were then promptly rewarded, inclined men to a
                  favorableconsideration of his claim. To Arnold's abusive appeal to congress,for he
                  appealed there, Mr Gerry replied, and after exhibiting with greatcalmness the
                  reasons of his decisions on his accounts, concluded witha severe reprehension of
                  the conduct of his assailant. "If," said he,"the faithful discharge of our
                  official duty, unpleasant enough initself, is to bring with it the liability of
                  personal attack of men whohave neither honesty in their public dealings nor
                  curtesy in privatelife, it might be well to abolish all guards on the treasury,
                  &amp; admitrapacity &amp; crime to help themselves at pleasure." This was intrepid
                  lan==guage at the period, &amp; must be sound doctrine at all times.On the 14th of
                  January 1778, in a letter to a friend, he says, "I am worndown with fatigue, &amp;
                  have been waiting with some impatience to returnto Massachusetts; but I have
                  wished to see certain measures accomplishedbefore I left congress; when those were
                  finished, others presented themselvesequally important &amp; I waited for them,
                  &amp; so on; but this mode of travellingwill never get me home. I must therefore
                  determine at all events to leavethis place in the spring." The 24th of April he
                  says, "I wish to see a return ofsome of my colleagues, in order to obtain such
                  relaxation from business,as at length has become indispenably necessary for
                  preserving my health.Two years constant attention to the business of congress
                  &amp; the board ofthe treasury, the members of which have been unequal in number
                  to theduties required, with opportunity for very little exercise, israther
                  hazardous to the constitution, &amp; I feel the effects of it." The26th of May he
                  says, "I had before this thot to have set off for Massa=chusetts, but have not
                  been able to break away from the incessant la==bors which occupy me day &amp;
                  night much of this time &amp; close applicationwas devoted to forming &amp;
                  vindicating the articles of confederation betweenthe States." Near the close of
                  1779 he was appointed at the head of the com==mittee chosen by Massachusetts to
                  meet delegates from other statesat Philadelphia, to devise a corrective for the
                  deplorable state of thepaper currency.</p>
               <p>On the 19th of February 1780, upon the question of proportioning sup==plies to be
                  furnished by the several states &amp; the value of them,  he movedthat the prices
                  should conform to those agreed upon by a conventionpreviously held at New Haven.
                  This motion was objected to as beingout of order; on the question of order, he
                  requested the yeas &amp; nays, but congressrefused to record them. This course he
                  considered improper &amp; injuriousto Massachusetts, who he thot was required to
                  contribute more then her equalproportion to the common cause. He therefore on the
                  5th July left congresswhere he had devoted, without recess or intermission four
                  years &amp; a half tohis official labors for which he received about four thousand
                  dollars specievalue.</p>
               <p>Soon after his return to Massachusetts, he made his complaint to theirgeneral
                  assembly; the house approved of his conduct, &amp; voted to sustain hiscomplaint
                  but the council probably thinking the opinion expressed by thepopular branch would
                  answer all the purposes proposed by the measurelet the resolve lie on the table.
                  This course did not satisfy Mr Gerry. InNovember he was re-elected delegate to
                  congress, but declined the appoint==ment, assigning as a reason that the rights
                  &amp; prerogatives of the state hadbeen invaded in his person, &amp; no redress
                  had on his own application, &amp; nodemand had been made by his constituents. The
                  court resolved that theyapproved of the high sense which he had of his right of
                  priviledge, andinstructed their delegates to make such representation to congress
                  as the im==portance of the subject required. Their delegates accordingly presented
                  aremonstrance &amp; protest against the proceedings of congress, which wasplaced
                  in their files. Tho Mr Gerry was absent, congress appointed him amember of the
                  committee to visit the army.</p>
               <p>On the 31st of January 1781 he was elected a member of the AmericanAcademy of Arts
                  &amp; Sciences. In October he was elected a representativeby the inhabitants of
                  Marblehead, &amp; a senator by the county of Essex, tothe Massachusetts
                  legitature. The office of senator he declined, but that of representative he
                  accepted. In April 1782 he was again electedsenator, but again declined the
                  office.</p>
               <p>The 21st of June 1781 he was again elected a delegate to the congress of theUnited
                  States; but the controversy which induced him to leave congress thepreceeding year
                  not being settled, nor such measures adopted by theState in relation to it as he
                  thot satisfactory, he formally declined theappointment; but the legislature did
                  not accept his decline. In June 1782the legislature re-appointed him delegate to
                  congress; &amp; in June 1783 theyagain re-appointed him. Yielding to the
                  solicitations of personal &amp; politicalfriends, &amp; satisfied at length with
                  the measures which had been ta==ken on his remonstrance, he resumed his seat in
                  congress on thethird of November following, where he remained till some time
                  inSeptember 1785, when he closed his career in the old congress. It is saidthat at
                  the age of less than forty two years he had been longer a mem==ber of congress
                  than any other man in it. He was opposed to the societyof Cincinnati-he considered
                  it too aristocratical for our institutions,&amp; as having a tendency to introduce
                  an order of nobility into the country.He preserved his habits of industry, &amp;
                  close attention to every subjectthat was moved in congress; he transcribed with
                  his own hands theirpublic &amp; private proceedings during every day of his
                  attendance. Congressappointed him one of the commissioners to settle with the
                  contractorsof the army; but he declined the appointment.</p>
               <p>Before he left congress, but after he was more than forty years old, hemarried a
                  daughter of James Thompson of New York. By her he hada numerous family of
                  children. She, and three sons, &amp; six daughterssurvived him.</p>
               <p>In May 1785 he was elected a member of the Senate of Masachusetts,but declined the
                  office; observing he was elected a representative, whichhe intended to accept as
                  soon as his term of delegate to congress shouldexpire.</p>
               <p>In 1786 he was appointed by the legislature of Massachusetts one of theirdelegates
                  to meet delegates from the other States at Annapolis the first ofSeptember, to
                  consider the commerce of the United States, &amp; how far auniform system of
                  commercial regulations was necessary, &amp; to report abill upon the subject to
                  congress. The delegates from Massachusetts con==sidered the plan too limited &amp;
                  inefficient for the purpose, &amp; severally declinedthe appointments. At the
                  meeting only five States attended at Annapolis;&amp; nothing was done, except
                  recommending the States to appoint a conventionto meet the next year at
                  Philadelphia.</p>
               <p>The general court of Masachusetts appointed him a delegate to the con==vention,
                  which met at Philadelphia &amp; formed the constitution of the UnitedStates. On
                  the 29th of May 1787 he attended &amp; took part in the business anddebates of
                  that assembly; but having arrived at the conclusion in his own mindthat it did not
                  comport with the well being of the country, with regret. But without hesitation,
                  he declined signing the constitution. In his letterof the 18th of October
                  following to the president of the Senate &amp; speaker ofthe house of
                  representatives of Massachusetts, he stated his objectionsto the constitution in a
                  frank &amp; candid manner, addressed to theirunderstanding, not their passions.
                  "My principal objections," he says,"to the plan are, there is no adequate
                  provision for a representationof the people; that they have no security for the
                  right of election; thatsome of the legislature are ambiguous, &amp; others
                  indefinite &amp; dangerous,that the executive is blended with, &amp; will have an
                  undue influ==ence over, the legislature; that the judicial departments will
                  beoppressive; that treaties of the highest importance may be formed bythe
                  president with the advice of two thirds of a quorum of the Senate;&amp; that the
                  system is without the security of a bill of rights." Butin the conclusion he says,
                  "I shall only add, that as the publicwelfare requires a better constitution than
                  the confederation, Ishall think it my duty, as a citizen of Massachusetts, to
                  supportthat which shall be finally adopted, sincerely hoping it willsecure the
                  liberty &amp; happiness of America."</p>
               <p>The convention of Massachusetts, which met the 9th of January 1788,to decide the
                  question whether they would ratify the constitution, onthe 14th of that month
                  voted that Mr Gerry "be requested to take aseat in the convention, to answer any
                  questions of fact from timeto time, that the convention may ask, respecting the
                  passing of theconstitution;" &amp; appointed a committee to request him to attend,
                  &amp; heattended accordingly. On the 18th the convention voted that his an==swers
                  should be in writing; with which he complied. On the 22d hewrote a long letter to
                  the convention respecting the constitution; towhich objections &amp; some pointed
                  remarks were made; &amp; no furthercommunications appear to have been made by him.
                  His oppositionto the constitution exposed him to the censure of many of his
                  formerpolitical friends, &amp; to much abuse in the journals of the day. He
                  feltseverely the revulsion of public opinion, &amp; the loss of popularity.At the
                  first election of representatives to congress under that consti==tution, he was
                  brot forward as a candidate; but at the first meetingsin Middlesex there was no
                  choice, &amp; previous to the second his friendsagain named him. He then
                  published, under his own signature, amanly address to the electors, requesting
                  such of them as were dispo==sed to vote for him to turn their attention to some
                  other candidate ex==plicitly declaring that an election would by no means be
                  agreeable to him.After mentioning the unjust accusations &amp; abuse which had
                  beenheaped upon him, for acting according to his own judgment re==specting the
                  constitution of the United States, he says, "Somehave endeavored to represent me
                  as an enemy to the constitution; than which nothing is more remote from truth.</p>
               <p>Since the commencement of the revolution, I have been solicitiousfor an efficient
                  federal government, conceiving that without it wemust be a divided &amp; unhappy
                  people. A government too democraticalI have deprecated; but wished for one that
                  possessed powers sufficientfor the welfare of the union, &amp; at the same time so
                  balanced as to se==cure the governed from the rapacity &amp; domination of lawless
                  &amp; insolentambition. To an unconstitutional ratification I was therefore
                  opposed,because thereby every necessary amendment would be precarious.But as the
                  system is adopted, I am clearly of opinion that every citi==zen of the ratifying
                  States is in duty bound to support it, &amp; that anopposition to a due
                  administration of it would not only be unjustifiablebut highly criminal.</p>
               <p>"Amendments every citizen has a right to urge without enciting aspirit of
                  prosecution, which is unnecessary in a good cause, &amp; never gainsproselytes in
                  a bad one. Every friend of a vigorous government, as Iconceive, must be desirous
                  of such amendments as will remove thejust apprehensions of the people, &amp;
                  secure their confidence &amp; affection. Todefeat amendments of this description,
                  must be in effect to defeat theconstitution itself. When the question on
                  amendments shall havereceived a constitutional decision; I shall cheerfully
                  acquiese, &amp; in anyevent, shall be happy to promote the interests of the
                  respectable countyof Middlesex, of this commonwealth, &amp; of the United
                  States.</p>
               <p>"The part, which I have had to act, &amp; the uncandid treatment, &amp; thewhich I
                  have received in this matter will, I trust, justify me in beingthus explicit, for
                  I am conscious that every part of my political conducthas had for its object, the
                  public welfare."</p>
               <p>At the second meeting he was elected by a small majority. In his letter
                  ofacceptance to the governor he says. "I am deeply impressed with thehonorable
                  testimony of the electors of Middlesex, after I had repeatedlyinformed them of my
                  declining the appointments. This however has placedme in a situation, which of all
                  others I wished to avoid; being therebyreduced to the disagreeable alternative of
                  disappointing my fellowcitizens; who have conferred on me their suffrages, or of
                  filling a place,which the most cogent reasons had urged me to decline. Under
                  thesecircumstances, in the critical state of public affairs, I have preferredthe
                  latter, being determined to sacrifice every personal consideration,to the
                  acceptance of the office; that desirous as I am of the establishmentof a federal
                  government, no act of mine may have the least appearanceof impeding it." To his
                  confidential friends he wrote on this subject inthe same strain; &amp; there is
                  not the slightert reason to doubt thetruth &amp; sincerty of his declaration.</p>
               <p>On the 8th of April 1789 he took his seat in congress. When someof the members
                  were for considering the subject of amendements.before they had passed the laws
                  necessary to carry the new government into full effect, he opposed that object. In
                  the course ofdebate he said, "I am of opinion that we should dispatch the
                  importantsubjects now on the table, &amp; reserve the great questions concerning
                  theconstitution; to a period of tranquility &amp; leisure. It is indeed a
                  mo==mentuos subject, &amp; very near my heart, &amp; I shall be glad to setabout
                  it as speedily as possible; but I would not stay the operation ofgovernment on
                  that account. I think our political ship should first begot under way, &amp; that
                  she be not suffered to rot at the wharf, till shebeats off her rudder, or runs a
                  wreck on the shore. I wish an earlyday may be assigned for the consideration of
                  amendments, to prevent thenecessity, which the States may feel themselves under of
                  calling a new con==vention. I am not one of those facinated admirers of the system
                  whoconsider it all perfection; I am not so blind or so uncandid, that Icannot see,
                  or will not acknowlege it has beauties. It partakes of hu==manity; there is
                  blended in it virtue &amp; vice, excellence &amp; error. If itis referred to a new
                  convention, we risk some of its best properties.My opinion was openly given, that
                  it ought not to have been ratifiedwithout amendments, but as the matter now
                  stands, I am firmly ofopinion that the salvation of America depends on the
                  establishmentof this government, whether amended or not. If this constitution,
                  whichis now ratified, be not supported, I despair of ever having a governmentfor
                  these United States."</p>
               <p>In 1791 he was re-elected a representative to congress, &amp; held the officetill
                  the 3d of March 1793. Having served four years, he declined are-election.</p>
               <p>In the years 1796 &amp; 1804 he was chosen an elector of president &amp; vice
                  presi==dent of the United States.</p>
               <p>On the 22d of June 1797 he was appointed envoy extraordinary jointly withPinkney
                  &amp; Marshall to France. Nothing could have been more unexpectedto him than this
                  appointment, which he reluctantly accepted; &amp; on the9th of August following
                  embarked for that country. On the 4th Octoberthe thee envoys met in Paris, &amp;
                  the next day announced then arrivalto Talleyrand the minister of foreign affairs,
                  &amp; requested an opportunityto present their letters of evidence. Three days
                  after they had an interviewwith the minister, delivered the letters of evidence,
                  &amp; received cards of hos==pitality. In a day or two the private &amp;
                  confidential secretary of the mi==nister intimated to the secretary of one of the
                  envoys, that some partof the president's speech to congress required an
                  explanation; &amp; that theenvoys would not probably have an audience tell the
                  negotiation wasfinished. Anonymous persons, afterwards designated by X.Y.&amp;Z,
                  calledupon the envoys, &amp; proposed that they should give a softening turn to
                  thepresidents speech; make a loan of some millions of money to the Frenchtreasury
                  &amp; a gratuity of fifty thousand pounds sterling to certain high officers
                  ofgovernment, for distribution to prominent individuals. The envoys
                  promptlyresolved they would not purchase the right of negotiation. It was
                  intimated to Mr Gerry thot Talleyrand expected to have seen the American
                  envoy&amp; to have conferred with them individually on the affairs of the
                  mission.Gerry communicated the fact to Pinkney &amp; Marshall; they advised him
                  tocall, but declined going themselves. He reluctantly consented, &amp; had
                  severalinterviews with Tallyrand, at which they occasionally discussed
                  therelations of the United States &amp; France.</p>
               <p>After waiting thirty days, one of the envoys proposed to address the mi==nister in
                  an official note, requesting his attention to their situation,&amp; demanding that
                  measures should be taken to open the negotiation.Mr Gerry was of opinion it would
                  be useless; but signed with the otherenvoys a letter to the minister. To this
                  letter no answer was returned;but they were given to understand it was laid before
                  the executivedirectory, who would command their minister what steps to
                  pursue.Talleyrand informed Mr Gerry that no treaty would be made withthe envoys,
                  without an apology for the presidents speech, or an equa== valent; but that a
                  voluntary offer of a loan would be accepted asan equavalent. In consequence of
                  Gerry's visit to Talleyrand, the latterinvited the former to one of his customary
                  dinners, &amp; Mr Gerry afterwardsreturned the civility; but his separation from
                  his colleagues wasso unpleasant, that with a single exception he afterwards
                  declinedall personal attention to Talleyrand. All three of the envoys signeda
                  report to the government of the United States, that there was no prospectof
                  effecting the object of their mission, without the payment of a largesum of
                  money.</p>
               <p>On the 4th of February 1798, Talleyrand invited Mr Gerry to call uponhim; at their
                  meeting Talleyrand, after enjoining profound secrecy, informedGerry that the
                  directory had determined not to treat with Pinkney &amp; Marshallbut were willing
                  to commence negotiations with him. On the 27thof that month the envoys demanded of
                  Tallyrand an audience; &amp; onthe 2d &amp; 6th of March were admitted. He
                  insisted on a loan. Pinkney andMarshall were decidedly against it; but Gerry
                  appeared, at the conferences,silent on the subject. But when the envoys were
                  together by themselves,Gerry stated his opinion, that he thot a loan preferable to
                  a war, &amp; wastherefore willing to open negotiation upon the basis of a loan,
                  &amp; whena treaty was formed not agree to it without the sanction of our
                  govern==ment; but the other two envoys met the proposition with an un==qualified
                  negative. On the 18th of that month Talleyrand in an officialletter to the envoys
                  avows the opinion that the directory will not treatwith the three envoys, but with
                  one of them. The envoys not being accredited,but exposed to personal &amp;
                  official mortifications of a humiliating kind, requested that letters of safe post
                  should be granted to them individuallyor to such as they pleased. Letters were
                  accordingly granted to Pinkney &amp; Marshall, but not to Gerry; &amp; the two
                  former soon after embarked for the United States.</p>
               <p>On the 3d of April Talleyrand wrote Gerry that he believed the other twoenvoys had
                  withdrawn from the French territories, &amp; expressed a desireto resume
                  communications with him upon the interests of France &amp;the United States. The
                  next day Gerry informed him that as an indi==vidual he would confer, but the
                  commission being jointly to threeenvoys, as a minister he had no authority. On the
                  20th he wrote Talley==rand, That as his colleagues from necessity had left Paris;
                  to prevent arupture between the two nations he had consented to remain; buthis
                  conferences must be informal-&amp; that he should communicate themto his
                  government, but without official authority. Talleyrand abandonedthe demand of a
                  loan, &amp; the explanation of the president's speech; andannounced the
                  willingness of the government to give Mr Gerry a publicreception.</p>
               <p>On the 3d of May Mr Gerry in a letter to Mr King says, "I cannot saywhat will be
                  the opinion of the president, or of his constitutients, re=­=specting my conduct
                  in remaining here, but I will do nothing thatI cannot justify to my own mind,
                  &amp; which I am not clearly convincedought to merit their approbation. I have no
                  personal views in re==maining, &amp; the moment I can reconcile this government to
                  mydeparture, I shall embark for the United States."</p>
               <p>The circumstance of his remaining in France after the other envoyshad left it,
                  &amp; the apprehension that he would do something that wouldcompromit the honor or
                  interest of our country, excited the people tocensure him with great severity. To
                  a gentleman who had forwardedto him, by express, the dispatches published in the
                  United States, advisinghim to withdraw from France before their contents were made
                  known&amp; urging the danger of his situation, he writes, "I have received
                  yourletter with copies of the dispatches enclosed. The prospect of a ten
                  year'simprisonment would not induce me to quit this country as a fugitive."In his
                  conferences with Talleyrand he displayed tatents, information,industry, prudence,
                  &amp; uncompromising integrity. On the eve of hostilitiesbetween the two nations
                  his zeal, his penetration, &amp; cool perseverance,laid the foundation for an
                  accomodation. The minister having givenhim a positive assurance of the reception
                  of another minister, with therespect due to the nation he should represent, he on
                  the 10th of June de==manded his pass-ports; but the government of France, under
                  various pre==tents, delayed it till the 26th of July, when he left Paris for
                  Havre.There he received an arrete from the French government restrainingthe
                  irregular &amp; vexatious conduct of privateers in the West Indian Seas&amp;
                  assurances given that all other anangements should conform to the just
                  expectations of the United States. The benefits which Mr Gerryconsidered as
                  resulting from his residence in that country was, an expressrenunciation on the
                  part of France of loans; of reparation for the presi==sidents speech; a
                  renuniciation of a demand for the United States toassume debts due her citizens; a
                  disclaimer of any desire that weshould dissolve the British treaty; an admission
                  of our claim for captureson the want of a role d'equipage; advances towards a new
                  negotia==tion; &amp; the actual preservation of peace.</p>
               <p>On the first day of October he arrived at Boston; &amp; on the 18th ofthat month
                  in a letter to the secretary of State, giving an account ofhis mission says_ "I
                  was informed that an immediate rupturewould be the result of my departure from
                  France; &amp; the same com==munication being again made, with information, that if
                  I wasdetermined not to negotiate seperately, this government would besatisfied
                  with my residence here, untill the government of the UnitedStates could take their
                  measures. I consented to this from public con==siderations solely; for every
                  private one was opposed to it. In myembarrassed situation, not losing sight of the
                  great object of ourmission, a reconciliation with this powerful republic. I have
                  takena position, by which I meant to ascertain, if possible, without
                  com=­=promitting the government of the United States, or myself, the ulti=­=timate
                  views of France with respect to them. It would havebeen impossible for me under
                  existing circumstances to have consentedto a seperate negotiation, had the
                  provision been made in our powers&amp; instructions: for two of my colleagues, one
                  from the southern, &amp; theother from the middle states, having been sent back, I
                  could have hadno prospect of forming a treaty, which would have given
                  generalsatisfaction to my country; &amp; I could never undertaken any
                  nego==ciation, without that prospect. It is therefore incumbent on me todeclare,
                  that should the result of my endeavors present to our govern=­=ment more pleasing
                  prospects, it is nevertheless, my firm determi==nation to proceed no further in
                  this negotiation."</p>
               <p>Tho the mission was very unpleasant to each of the envoys, it wasuseful to the
                  United States-it opened a way for the termination ofhostile feelings, &amp; the
                  preservation of the peace &amp; honor of our country. Pre==sident Adams, the
                  elder, some years after says, Mr Gerry "finallysaved the peace of the nation, for
                  he alone discovered &amp; furnished evi==dence that X.Y &amp;Z. were employed by
                  Talleyrand; &amp; he alonebrot home the direct, formal, &amp; official
                  assuran==ces upon which the subsequent commission proceeded &amp; peace
                  made."After his return from France a number of his friends were desirous that he
                  should be candidate for representative to congress; buthe positively declined it.
                  In April 1800 &amp; 1801 he was supportedas candidate for governor of
                  Massachusetts, but the opposing can==didate succeeded by a small majority: in the
                  last of those yearsof 45,816 votes Gerry had 20,169.</p>
               <p>He spent his time at his farm in Cambridge in philosophicalretirement, attending
                  to his favorite pursuits, the education of hischildren, &amp; the cultivation of
                  his land. But in his retirement hewas unfortunate. A friend for whom he had become
                  suretyfor a large amount, failed, &amp; left him with a weight of
                  pecuniaryobligation, from which he was never able to extricate himself.Indeed, at
                  his discease he left to his family only his example andhis fame.</p>
               <p>Immediately after the attack made in 1808 by the British shipLeopard upon the
                  American frigate Chesapeake, there was a greatmeeting held in Boston on the
                  occasion. Mr Gerry being there,but not in the assembly, was appointed presiding
                  officer. Afterbeing conducted to the chair, he observed "I had not anticipatedthat
                  at my time of life, there could have been a scene like ofthe present, but I yield
                  to the call that is made on me, as I holdit to be the duty of every citizen, tho
                  he may not have but one dayto live, to devote that day to his country.</p>
               <p>In August 1810 Harvard college conferred on him the degree of doctorof laws; the
                  people, in the preceeding April, having elected him governorof Massachusetts, on
                  the duties of which he entered the 2d of June. Inappointments to office, he
                  respected the claims of his political friendswhom he found to have been heretofore
                  almost entirely excluded;but of the incumbents holding their place at the will of
                  the exe==cutive, no one was disturbed in the enjoyment of his situation.A strong
                  effort was made by influential individuals to change thegovernor's policy in this
                  respect, &amp; there were not wanting thosewho expressed their dissatisfaction at
                  the tolerance he was disposedto observe. But their disapprobation was without
                  effect: his policywas to effect a conciliation between the people &amp; the
                  administrationof the government of the United States.</p>
               <p>In April 1811 he was re-elected governor. The opposition of the fede=­=ralists of
                  Massachusetts, to the administration of the governmentof the Unted States, had
                  become not only active but violent. The go==vemor in his speech, of the 7th of
                  June, to the legislature, speakingof the appointments he had made, says, "To
                  diminish, &amp; if possible toexterminate party spirit, the executive of this
                  commonwealth, during in the last year, has confirmed in his place, or re-appointed
                  within or requisite, every state officer under his control, who has been correct
                  inhis conduct, &amp; faithful to his trust; disregarding his polities, &amp;
                  requir=­=ing only his support of the federal &amp; state constitutions,
                  govern==ments &amp; laws, with a due regard to the rights of officers
                  andindividuals subject to his official discretion. But it cannotbe expected of any
                  executive, so far to disregard the sound obli==gations of duty &amp; honor, as to
                  preserve in official stations suchindividuals as would abuse the influence of
                  their public characters,by sanctioning resistance to laws, or by such other
                  conduct as willbeguile peaceable &amp; happy citizens into a state of civil
                  warfare.In all the branches of the government the republicans had a de==cided
                  majority, &amp; to aid their partizans passed laws removing she==riffs &amp;
                  clerks of court from office, &amp; requiring the governor andcouncil to appoint
                  men to fill those offices. Impelled by theconsiderations mentioned in his speech
                  &amp; the zeal of his partizans,he turned out some men from office &amp; appointed
                  some others, whichif left to the unbiased exercise of his own judgment it is
                  proba=­=ble he would not have done.</p>
               <p>On the 25th of April 1812, in compliance with a requisition fromthe government of
                  the United States, he promptly issued orders to themilitia officers to detach ten
                  thousand men to be organized andready to march at a moments warning for the
                  defence of the coun==try. In a private letter of that date he says, "We have been
                  longenough at peace; we are loosing our spirit, our character, &amp;
                  ourindependence. We are degenerating into a mere nation of traders,&amp; are
                  forgetting the honor of our ancestors, &amp; the interest of poste==rity. We must
                  be roused by some great event that may stir upthe ancient spirit of the people.
                  Policy has kept us quiet till itceases to be policy. Weakness &amp; exhaustion
                  prevented us from nobledaring, &amp; it was wise in us to temporize untill we
                  gained strength&amp; vigor. We have now grown to manhood, &amp; it will be
                  shameful inthe man to bear what the child might submit to without dishonor."At the
                  April election this year for governor, of 104,156 votes he had51,326, but the
                  opposing federal candidate was elected by a majorityof 1,370.</p>
               <p>He possessed a sagacity, a fortitude, an inflexibility, &amp; an
                  indefatigableapplication which few men can equal. Forming his opinions
                  withdeliberation, he yielded them with reluctance. Feeling the convictionarising
                  from thorough investigation, it was not easy to change his results.</p>
               <p>The tenacity with which he clung to such sentiments as his judgmentapproved was at
                  times too determined, &amp; probably obstinate. This tendencywas increased by
                  another, which was the weakest trait of his mind.He was habitually suspicious,
                  &amp; this habit increased as he advancedin years. There was little in such a
                  state of mind of the art of acquiringpopularity, &amp; still less in letting it be
                  seen. They who were associatedwith him were often oppressed with a conviction that
                  he was doubtfulof their sincerity, &amp; this feeling on their part, generated a
                  state of thingswhich otherwise would not have existed. It is something anomalousin
                  the history of character, that an individual punctiliiously uprightin his own
                  conduct, should entertain so many doubts of the sincerityof others.</p>
               <p>In religion he was a liberal episcopalian-willing that those whodiffered from him
                  should conform to their own opinions. In his temperhe was naturally ardent &amp;
                  impetuous; but subjected his passions to thedictates of his judgment. Belonging to
                  that school of manners, whichcommenced under the royal government, &amp; perfected
                  its pupils in thecamp &amp; cabinet of the revolution, regulating the deportment
                  withcurtesy towards others, &amp; a personal dignity that never lost its
                  self=respect, lofty without arrogance, affable without familiarity, hewas at all
                  times &amp; under all circumstances, entitled to the character ofa real
                  gentleman.</p>
               <p>On the 8th of June 1812, at a meeting of severty six members of congress,all but
                  two of them voted to nominate him as a candidate for vicepresident of the United
                  States; &amp; a committee immediately wrote him reque==ting his consent. In his
                  letter to them, of the 11th he consented, observing"That in a republic, the
                  service of each citizen is due to the state, evenin profound peace, &amp; much
                  more so when the nation stands on thethreshold of war." On the first wednerday of
                  December of 217 electoral voteshe had 131, &amp; was elected; &amp; on the 4th
                  March 1813 took the oath of officeat his own house. He was a zealous, firm,
                  effective supporter of the warto it he devoted his time &amp; all the energies of
                  his mind. The24th of May, the first day of the session, he took his seat as
                  presiding officer in the Senate ofthe United States, &amp; continued till the
                  senate adjourned on the 2d ofAugust. As a presiding officer he was not
                  distinguished; but he renderedgreat service in supporting the government &amp; the
                  rights of the nation.During his residence at Washington, the private letter he
                  received fromhis friends, &amp; from applicants for office, were numerous. The
                  mere read==ing was fatiguing &amp; oppressive, &amp; often deprived him of
                  bothrest &amp; exercise. He politely answered as many of them as he was able.</p>
               <p>There was a town in Massachusetts incorporated by his namebut in 1814 the town
                  petitioned legislature to change its nameto Phillipstown, alledging that Gerry
                  while chief magistrate hadrendered "the name itself a term of odium &amp;
                  reproach," "&amp; requestingthat it might no longer bear his hateful name." That a
                  town shoulduse such virulent language against a man strictly honest &amp;
                  thesecond officer in the government of the nation, &amp; that the
                  legislatureshould so far approve of it as to grant their request, can be
                  imputedonly to the blindness &amp; madness of party spirit, which then prevailedin
                  both. Such proceedings reflect more distance on the petitioners &amp;
                  thelegislature, than reproach on Mr Gerry.</p>
               <p>Mr Gerry attended the second &amp; third sessions of the Senate; and on the 22nd
                  of November 1814 provided during the whole of a long debate, with hisusual spirit,
                  &amp; in the enjoyment of accustomed health. On returningto his lodgings he
                  complained of slight indisposition, but amusedhimself thro the evening in
                  arranging the letters of the day, &amp; in acheerful conversation with the immates
                  of the house. He conversedabout his family in Massachusetts, &amp; taking from his
                  bosom a minia==ture, which was always suspended round his neck when theoriginal
                  was absent, &amp; had hitherto, with a peculiar delicacy offeeling, been his own
                  personal secret, he spoke of it with an in==terest which shew that altho the
                  surpassing beauty delineatedon the picture might have first charmed the
                  imagination, moreenduring qualities had left the impress of affection on his
                  heart.He rested well thro the night, &amp; breakfasted as usual with the fa==mily
                  on the morning of the 23rd, &amp; altho he spoke of some vagueindications of
                  disease, he did not consider them sufficient to preventhis taking his seat in the
                  Senate, at the hour in which it was tomeet. The carriage coming to cany him to the
                  capitol rather earlierthan usual, he directed the coachman on his way there, to
                  stop at theoffice of the register of the treasury, at which he had some business
                  thatrequired his attention. This being arranged he returned to his carriage,&amp;
                  had proceeded but a short distance, when a sudden extravasationof blood took place
                  upon the lungs, &amp; terminated his life in twentyminutes, almost without a
                  struggle, &amp; apparently without pain, in theseventy first year of his age.</p>
               <p>The next day he was buried, under the direction of a committee ofthe Senate, in
                  the city of Washington. Congress afterwards erected amonument of white marble over
                  his remains, with the following in==scription. "The tomb of Elbridge Gerry. vice
                  president of the United States, who died suddenly in this city, November 23, 1814,
                  on his wayto the capitol as president of the Senate, aged seventy years.
                  Thusfulfilling his own memorable injunction. It is the duty of everyman, tho he
                  may have but one day to live, to devote that day to thegood of his country.</p>
               <p/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>